Guide to the John Quincy Adams Nadenbousch Papers, 1821-1932
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John Quincy Adams Nadenbousch papers 1821-1932
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Nadenbousch, John Quincy Adams, 1824-1892.
8.0 Linear Feet 3284 Items
Confederate officer and businessman, of Martinsburg, W. Va.
Correspondence, accounts, receipts, statements, muster rolls, orders, genealogical notes, and other personal, business, and military papers, of Nadenbousch and of his family. The bulk of the collection consists of business papers, mostly relating to Nadenbousch's flour mill and distillery. Includes material concerning the Berkeley Border Guards (later Co. D., 2d Regt., Virginia Infantry) and the Stonewall Brigade; public affairs in Martinsburg, W. Va.; the Berkeley Co. Agricultural and Mechanical Association; and activities of the West Virginia legislature.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Quincy Adams Nadenbousch Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1934-1949.
Biographical Note
Confederate officer and businessman, of Martinsburg, W. Va.
Collection Overview
Papers of John Quincy Adams Nadenbousch, his son-in-law, Alexander Parks, Jr., and other members of his family. The collection contains material relating to the operation of flour mills by John Q. A. Nadenbousch before the Civil War; the constitution of the Berkeley Border Guards formed in Berkeley County, Virginia, in 1859, and items relating to the subsequent service of that unit in the Civil War as a company of the 2nd Virginia Regiment, including letters of General Thomas Jonathan Jackson to his officers, commissary accounts, muster rolls, provost marshal records, and a manuscript draft of a report by John Q. A. Nadenbousch as colonel of the 2nd Virginia Regiment describing the experiences of that regiment in the fight at Culp's Hill, July 2, 1863, during the battle of Gettysburg; correspondence of John Q. A. Nadenbousch as agent of the Hannis Distilling Company of Baltimore, Maryland, engaged in the operation of a distillery at Martinsburg, West Virginia; letters relating to the management of the Grand Central Hotel in Martinsburg, 1878; and letters concerning John Q. A. Nadenbousch's general financial condition after the Civil War. Papers of Alexander Parks, Jr., concern his position as local agent for Hannis Distilling Company in Martinsburg after 1874; his participation in civic affairs in Martinsburg; and his work in the Democratic Party, including his election to the state senate of West Virginia in 1890. Papers of John Nadenbousch Parks, son of Alexander Parks, Jr., include letters to his family while he was a student at Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, Virginia, 1893, and letters, 1917, to John N. Parks while he was a member of the legislature of West Virginia. Letters, 1895, of Elise Parks, daughter of Alexander Parks, Jr., concern her life as a student at Virginia Female Institute, Staunton, Virginia. Volumes in the collection include a treasurer's notebook, 1852, of a local lodge of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows; a sheriff's account book, 1825-1841, from Jefferson County, West Virginia; an account of tax levies in Jefferson County; a ledger of John Q. A. Nadenbousch, 1872-1878; and notes and accounts of the Berkeley County Agricultural and Mechanical Association.
Correspondence includes a letter (1863) from U. S. senator Charles James Faulkner and two letters from Charlotte R. Pendleton of Berkeley Springs, Morgan Co., W. Va. One letter was written by her to Eldridge, her slave, expressing her concern for his well-being and her affection for him. The second is from Pendleton to Nadenbousch, begging him to send Eldridge home from the job for which he was conscripted in her absence.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Nadenbousch family
Berkeley County Agricultural and Mechanical Association (Berkeley County, W. Va.)
Confederate States of America -- Army -- Virginia Infantry Regiment, 2nd
Slaves -- West Virginia
Distilling industries -- West Virginia
Flour mills -- West Virginia -- Martinsburg
Industries -- West Virginia
Southern States -- Race relations -- History -- 19th century
Martinsburg (W. Va.)--Politics and government
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories
West Virginia -- Politics and government
Contents of Collection
- Papers, 1821-1925 and undated, (6 boxes)
  - Papers, 1821-1867, June (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1867 July-1871 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1872-1877 (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1878-1885 July (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1885 Aug.-1925 (Box 5)
  - Papers, undated (Box 6)
- Volumes, 1825-1932, (5 volumes)
  - Account book of Sheriff, Jefferson Co., W. Va., 1825-1841 (Volume S:2587)
  - Account book of tax levies, Jefferson Co., W. Va., undated (Volume S:2588)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church [?] class book, 1829-1848 (Volume M:2703)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church: Reports of Joint Hymnal Commission, 1932 (Volume M:2704)
  - Ledger, 1872-1878 (Volume L:3070)